<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>animation on globXblog</title>
    <link>http://example.org/tags/animation/</link>
    <description>Recent content in animation on globXblog</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-au</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://example.org/tags/animation/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>A postcard from Antarctica</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/antarctica/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 23 Mar 2022 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/antarctica/</guid>
      <description>Some time ago we’ve been lucky enough to receive the postcard below from the Mc Murdo Dry Valleys, in Antarctica (thank you so much Kaelin!</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Revealing Hidden Climate Indices</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/hci/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 29 Oct 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/hci/</guid>
      <description>In a previous post, we illustrated a widely used method called principal component analysis (PCA). This method can be used as an exploratory tool to summarise a dataset made of hundreds or thousands of time series into just a few ‘summary’ time series called principal components.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Finding hidden patterns in the data using principal components analysis</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/pca/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 11 Apr 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/pca/</guid>
      <description>In hydrology, it is frequent to analyse long time series coming from many sites. The figure below shows monthly streamflows at 207 sites in France for the period 1969-2014.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Folding and bending data</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/scatterplot-transformer/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 09 Mar 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/scatterplot-transformer/</guid>
      <description>In the fun with dendrograms post, a linear dendrogram is gradually bent into a full circle. This transformation isn’t specific to dendrograms and can be applied to any dataset.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>About the logo</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/about-the-logo/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 25 Jan 2021 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/about-the-logo/</guid>
      <description>The globXblog logo is a colourful doughnut that mimics an equaliser, referring to the sonification and visualisation part of the blog. In its core, a stormy icon represents the hydrological part of the blog.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Hydrology basics, episode 1: streamflow, precipitation and evapotranspiration</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/hydrology-basics-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Thu, 10 Dec 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/hydrology-basics-1/</guid>
      <description>How does water end up flowing in rivers? As schematized below, it is the result of processes that have taken place in the river basin, also known as a catchment and delineated by a red line in the figure.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Transforming a distance matrix into a map</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/transforming-a-distance-matrix-into-a-map/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 19 Sep 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/transforming-a-distance-matrix-into-a-map/</guid>
      <description>The map in the figure below shows the location of 195 hydrologic stations, which can be used to explore the hydrologic regimes of Australian rivers.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>El NiñOz</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/el-ninoz/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 26 Aug 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/el-ninoz/</guid>
      <description>The Pacific Ocean sometimes catches a fever in its Eastern tropical part (off the coasts between Central America and Peru): for extended periods of time, its surface waters are abnormally warm.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Fun with dendrograms</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/fun-with-dendrograms/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 20 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/fun-with-dendrograms/</guid>
      <description>A dendrogram is a way to visualise objects organised in a hierarchy. It looks like a tree where:
the leaves represent the objects of the dataset; the branches link similar leaves according to a given criterion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>How Australian rivers can be grouped into 4 main hydrologic regimes</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/australian-hydrologic-regimes/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 07 Jul 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/australian-hydrologic-regimes/</guid>
      <description>Investigating the hydrologic regime of 195 rivers in Australia revealed three types of flow seasonality. At some stations, the wettest period occurs during one particular season (winter or summer), whereas at others, similar flows are observed all year round.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Exploring the hydrologic regime of 195 rivers in Australia</title>
      <link>http://example.org/blog/australian-river-cruises/</link>
      <pubDate>Sun, 21 Jun 2020 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://example.org/blog/australian-river-cruises/</guid>
      <description>Plotting hydrologic regimes Most hydrologic studies start by determining the average quantity of water in rivers and how it is distributed throughout the year.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
